Guide to the Bertram Powers Papers and Photographs WAG.173
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Bertram Powers Papers and Photographs
1898-1990; bulk, 1961-1990
1961-1990
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Powers, Bertram
WAG.173
1 Linear Feet in one record carton.
Bertram Powers served as the President of the International Typographical Union's (ITU) Local 6 from 1961 to 1990. In December 1962, he called the first New York strike in the history of the ITU which targeted major dailies such as the New York Times, Journal-American and the Daily News. The strike ended in April 1963, thanks to a settlement hammered out by New York City Mayor Robert F. Wagner, Jr. In 1973, Powers negotiated a new contract which guaranteed lifetime employment for printers in exchange for allowing their jobs to be phased out by automation. Local 6 suffered a drastic decline in membership as automation took over and in 1987 merged with the Communications Workers of America. Powers retired in 1990 and died in December 2006. The collection contains appointment books, clippings relating to ITU negotiations and strikes, correspondence, election materials, personal documents and biographical information. The collection also contains photographs of Powers and ITU strikes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Bertram Powers in 1999. The accession numbers 1999.006, 1999.012 and NPA.2000.067 are associated with this gift.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Born in Cambridge, Massachusetts in 1922, Bertram Powers dropped out of high school to join the Civilian Conservation Corps. In 1939, after suffering severe leg and hip fractures when run over by a truck, he learned the printing trade at Fitchburg State Teachers College in Massachusetts.
After holding a series of short-term jobs, Powers moved to New York City in 1946, where he joined International Typographical Union (ITU) Local 6. First elected to the Executive Board of the Local in 1948, he then became vice-president in 1953, and president in 1961.
In December 1962, he called the first New York strike in the history of the ITU which targeted major dailies such as the New York Times, Journal-American and the Daily News. The infamous strike resulted in lost revenues of approximately $108 million for the newspapers involved and was blamed for the closing of the Daily Mirror, Herald-Tribune, Journal-American and World-Telegram, an accusation which Powers vehemently denied. Severe criticism from national leaders, including President John F. Kennedy, was leveled against Powers during the strike. The strike ended in April 1963, thanks to a settlement hammered out by New York City Mayor Robert F. Wagner, Jr. which included an increase in wages and the establishment of a common expiration date for all newspaper-union contracts. In exchange, Local 6 agreed to limited use of automated equipment.
In 1973, Powers negotiated a new contract which guaranteed lifetime employment for printers in exchange for allowing their jobs to be phased out by automation. Local 6 suffered a drastic decline in membership as automation took over, and in 1987 merged with the Communications Workers of America. Powers retired in 1990, and died in December 2006.
Sources:
Rivera, Ray. "Bertram Powers, Leader of Newspaper Printers, Dies at 84," New York Times, December 25, 2006, Sec. B.
Current Biography. "Powers, Bertram A(nthony)," January 1974: 28-31.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains appointment books, clippings relating to ITU negotiations and strikes, correspondence and election materials. Copies of personal documents, including Powers' will and marriage certificate are present in the collection. Also included are biographical information and interviews with Powers. Facsimiles of documents relating to the Typothetae of the City of New York, an association of master printers, are also included. A portion of this collection is made up of black and white photographs of Powers. Most of these photographs are either portraits of Powers or of Powers at meetings and lectures. Other photographs include images of the Typographical Workers Union Local 6 striking against the New York Times and the Mirror.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series. Each series is arranged alphabetically.
Series I: General Files
Series II: Photographs
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Other collections that Tamiment holds that are related to this collection are:
International Typographical Union, Local 6, Benefit Board Records (WAG.119) International Typographical Union, Local 6, Journal of Commerce Chapel (WAG.276)
New York (N.Y.).; Appointment books.; Interviews.; Correspondence.; Wills; Speeches.; Clippings (information artifacts); Strikes and lockouts -- Newspapers -- New York (N.Y.); Labor leaders -- New York (State) -- New York.; Photographs.; Strikes and lockouts |x Printers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Powers, Bertram; Typothetae of the City of New York; International Typographical Union. No. 6 (New York, N.Y.); Powers, Bertram
- Series I: General Files, 1868-1990; 1961-1990
  - Appointment Books, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Appointment Books, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Appointment Books, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Appointment Books, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Appointment Books, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Biographical Information, 1963-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings: General, 1966-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings: Strike, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clippings: Typographical Union Negotiations, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Clippings: Typographical Union Negotiations, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Election Materials, 1937-1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - International Typographers Union, 1962-1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Interviews, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Personal Documents, 1944-1990 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Typothetae of the City of New York: Documents (facsimiles), 1868-1898 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Front Page of the Daily News, Apr 7, 1965 (Box Shared Tamiment OS001)
- Series II: Photographs, undated, 1963, 1975, 1990
  - Candids, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Graphic, 1963, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Labor Day?, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Meetings, Lectures, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous Ephemera, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Portraits - Bertram Powers, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Portraits - Group, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Retirement Plaque - Photocopy, Jun 5, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Strikes, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)